Finding Aid for Bureau of Industrial Relations (University of Michigan) records 1936-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bureau of Industrial Relations (University of Michigan) records 1936-1972, 1936-1960
University of Michigan. Bureau of Industrial Relations.
3 linear feet
The Bureau of Industrial Relations established in the School of Business Administration as a center of information on employer-employee relations. Records include membership lists, and correspondence and other papers relating to conferences sponsored by the Bureau and publications of the Bureau.
8726 Bimu C222 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were received from the unit in 1962. Printed materials have been received in periodic acquisitions. Donor no. 3933.
The records are open for research.
The Bureau of Industrial Relations was established in 1935 as a center for information on employer-employee relations. It was financed with funds donated by the Earhart Foundation. For administrative purposes, the Bureau of Industrial Relations was a part of the School of Business Administration, but served the entire University. The aim of the Bureau was to be of help to all people and groups who were trying to deal with problems in industrial relations. Services were available to business executives, public agencies, labor organizations and students who were trying to obtain information regarding problems resulting from employer-employee relationships. The major activities of the Bureau of Industrial Relations included research in the field of industrial relations, information service provided through the special library of the Bureau, student instruction on campus, and conferences on topics of interest related to industrial relations.
In the 1940s and 1950s, the Bureau of Industrial Relations continued to grow. At this time, its main areas of activity expanded to include a continuing education program and the establishment of a Faculty Research Fellowship in Personnel Administration. The conference program also continued to grow and became a large portion of the activities of the Bureau.
John W. Riegal was the first Director of the Bureau of Industrial Relations and served until his retirement in 1959. He was succeeded by George Odiorne, who added the Center for Programmed Learning. By 1970, the Bureau was conducting seminars in cooperation with the School of Business Administration on 50 different topics. About five workshops or seminars were offered per week, amounting to more than 270 per year.
In 1972, the Board of Regents approved the replacement of the Bureau of Industrial Relations with the Division of Management Education.
The records of the Bureau of Industrial Relations document it's work in sponsoring research and educational conferences on industrial relations. The records include membership lists, and correspondence and other papers relating to conferences sponsored by the Bureau and publications of the Bureau.
Subjects:
Riegel, John W.; Industrial relations--United States.; University of Michigan. Bureau of Industrial Relations.
Genre/Form:
College publications.
- Conferences
  The Conferences series contains membership lists and correspondence regarding Industrial Relations conferences. Membership lists are organized by the company represented at conferences. These lists include the company name and address as well as the name and position of the individual representing the company. Later lists (1950/51-1951/52) are similar to notebooks, containing correspondence, mailing lists, notes, programs and meeting minutes pertaining to Conference Courses. Correspondence is organized according to the conference locations. Saginaw Conference Records include correspondence, notes, proceedings and miscellaneous items regarding Industrial Relations Conferences in Saginaw. Other records from the Bureau of Industrial Relations will be found in the School of Business Administration record group.
  - Clippings 1953-1959 (Box 1)
  - Conference Courses
    - Membership Lists
      - 1944/45-1951/52, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Conference on Industrial Relations
    - Notes 1950 (Box 1)
  - Conference Schedules 1956/57 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Battle Creek and Kalamazoo Conferences 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Conference 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Grand Rapids Conference 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Saginaw Conference 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Topics and Suggestions for Meetings 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1957 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases (Box 1)
  - Saginaw Conference Records 1947-1960 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters pertaining to the establishment of the Bureau of Industrial Relations.
  - 1935 (Box 1)
- Industrial Relations Library
  The Industrial Relations Library series contains annual reports which include statistical reports.
  - Annual Reports 1951-1970 (Box 1)
- Printed Materials
  Printed Materials of the Bureau of Industrial Relations date 1936-1972. Unit Publications include addresses and reports, and several short runs of various newsletters. Sub-Unit Publications contain materials produced by the Center for Programmed Learning for Business and the Industrial Relations Library.
  Some printed materials, such as the newsletters Personnel Management Abstracts and Human Resource Management continue under the control of the Division of Management Education. These materials will be found in the School of Business Administration record group.
  - Unit Publications
    - Addresses
      - Addresses on Industrial Relations, 1936-1961 Bulletins 1-29, 21 folders (Box 2)
      - Organizing and Developing the Management Team, Undated (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies
      - A Selected list of Books and Periodicals in the Field of Personnel Administration and Labor Management Relations, 1954-1968 (Box 2)
    - Brochures
      - Addresses on Industrial Relations, 1946-1958 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Research Fellowships in Industrial Relations Undated (Box 2)
      - General Undated, 1938 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Teaching and Research Appointments in Business Administration and Industrial Relations, 1956/57-1957/58 (Box 2)
      - Instruction Research and Services in Industrial Relations, Undated, 1958 (Box 2)
      - Major Subjects Discussed in Publications Received from Employers, Undated (Box 2)
      - Management Development Seminars 1968-1972 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Undated, 1953-1972 (Box 2)
      - Personnel Course 1960-1963 (Box 2)
      - Personnel Techniques Seminars 1961-1966 (Box 2)
      - Reference Service Undated, 1953-1969 (Box 2)
    - Catalogs
      - Research Publications in Industrial Relations, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Indexes
      - Reference Index to Published Information on Industrial Relations, 1936 (Box 2)
      - Index to Reference Material on Industrial Relations, 1938-1946 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Human Resource Management (Box 3)
        - 1972 v.11 (Box 3)
      - Industrial Relations Law Digest
        - 1972 v.15 (Box 3)
      - Industrial Manpower Planning
        - 1962-1963 v.1 (Box 3)
      - The Linking Pen
        - 1971 v.1-2 (Box 3)
      - Management of Personnel Quarterly
        - 1962-1964 v.1-3 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Industrial Relations Lecture Series 1966/67 (Box 3)
      - Personnel Management Abstracts
        - 1972 v.18 (Box 3)
    - Programs
      - Conferences on Industrial Relations in Battle Creek and Kalamazoo 1948-1965 (Box 3)
      - Conferences on Industrial Relations in Detroit 1945-1965 (Box 3)
      - Conferences on Industrial Relations in Flint 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Conferences on Industrial Relations in Grand Rapids 1945-1965 (Box 3)
      - Conferences on Industrial Relations in Saginaw 1946-1965 (Box 3)
      - Conferences on Personnel Management 1944-1957 (Box 3)
      - Seminar on Managers' Relations with Engineers and Scientists 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Riegal Reports
        - Wage Determination, [Report 1], 1937 (Box 3)
        - Salary Determination: Common Policies and Selected Practices in Forty American Corporations, Report 2, 1940 (Box 3)
        - Management, Labor and Technological Change..., Report 3, 1942 (Box 3)
        - Executive Development: A Survey of Experience in Fifty American Corporations, Report 5, 1952 (Box 3)
        - Labor Relations and Productivity in the Building Trades, Report 6, 1956 (Box 3)
        - Employee Interest in Company Success, Report 7, 1956 (Box 3)
        - Administration of Salaries for Engineers and Scientists, Report 8, 1958 (Box 3)
        - Intangible Rewards for Engineers and Scientists, Report 9, 1958 (Box 3)
        - Collective Bargaining as Viewed by Unorganized Engineers and Scientists, Report 10, 1959 (Box 3)
      - Selected Questions on the Social Security Act, 1936 (Box 3)
      - Selected Statements of Labor Policy, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Selection and Development of Foremen, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Washtenaw County, Michigan Labor Market - Characteristics, Forecast, and Problems 1964 (Box 3)
    - Reprints 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    - Center for Programmed Learning for Business
      - Brochures
        - Miscellaneous 1964-1969, Undated (Box 3)
      - Newsletters
        - Programmed Learning Bulletin, 1963-1965 v.1-2 (Box 3)
    - Industrial Relations Library
      - Bibliographies
        - Recommended Readings in Personnel Administration and Labor-Management Relations, 1970 (Box 3)